...and welcome to build
twenty fifteen today we're going to talk about how you can build faster and
more powerful cloud our apps with the windows ten app platform I'm so
dark I'm a program manager on the windows networking api team and this is
marjorie he's also member of our team and our team basically
bills all the apis that are app needs to talk to the network and to the cloud so
let's start this talk by understanding what we mean by cloud our apps.
Cloud our app is really any app that...content either from the internet or from
peer devices so you can think of these abs as
your news app your sports score apps or even things like book peer-to-peer chat
...peer-to-peer game and these are typically
build using networking apis that we provide in the windows platform, for example,
a peer-to-peer app...typically you sockets if you wanted to talk to a web service in the
cloud your typically use http.
Now what do we mean by we're making it faster and more capable.
So, we're going to provide higher performance sockets apis that led to do much faster
peer-to-peer communication we are also providing faster http.
And, this will help you improve the performance of your web services code.
And, finally we're adding new capabilities to
our background data transfer apis so in this talk we'll go
through these one by one going up the stack so we'll start with sockets will
then go over to http.
Then we'll talk about background transfer and finally
will hit a summary of some of the other improvements we have in this area.
So, first let's start with sockets so, you know,
that most apps will use sockets only when...the foreground
and that's because having sockets in the background is really expensive for the system.
In windows...we have taken steps to solve this problem what you can
now do is have your socket listening in the background even...is not
running and this enables really powerful scenarios so what let's look at what is happening your
app would create a socket when it's in the foreground and you will also
associated with the background tasks that you yourself have define.
Now...the...get suspended so when the user navigate away you would transfer the
ownership of the socket to a socket broker
socket broker is basically the name of...os component that's always a
live and listening to sockets even when...ad does not alone.
Now when there is activity on your socket, for example,
it gets closed or gets and incoming message the socket brokered detects that
...to launch the task that
you had associated with the socket the task and now access the socket
get ownership back do stuff on the socket and then return ownership to the broker.
Finally window foreground app is launched again or it resumes you can
get the ownership of the socket back and use...just like you were earlier and
they're really cool part is when you get the ownership from this of the socket back.
The data is still on the socket and the socket distill connect.
So, let's look at some code samples.
Let me use append.
So, you'd basically define a trigger that's a socket
activity trigger and this is a new class that we are defining in windows stand.
You would then build a background tasks that subscribes to this trigger.
Now when you create your socket you also
enable transfer ownership on that socket this basically tells
a system that hey you can let the ownership of my socket go from the foreground
...to the broker and to this background tasks that's named
Finally you would of course connector socket to the remote endpoint.
Now when the app is being suspended we are familiar with
the on suspending method that gets called when app is being suspended you'd basically
define a socket id which is a simple string.
And, you would then cancel all the tending io operations on the
socket this step is really important because if there are pending
io operations the ownership transfer to the socket broker will fail so
usually need to cancel all the pending ios and then transfer ownership to the socket
program now at this point
your apa suspended and the socket broker has ownership of your socket now assuming there's some
activity on the socket your background task gets launched so this is the code you would
...in the background task you'd basically...
the triggered details from the socket activity trigger.
And, then the socket information object in the details.
We'll tell you the reason...background task
...triggered so it could be that there was activity on the socket it could be that
...keep...so on and the background task you would have to handy each of these
cases...important to note that after you have handle.
The case you need to
transfer the ownership back to the broker and this is important because when
the aggregates resume it wants to find the socket with the broker so it can get
...back so here's how you do that encode once...foreground
...resumes you.
Basically access
this static apis socket activity information with the socket id that
...defined earlier this basically tells the socket broker that
...of all the sockets that you have ownership off give
me back the socket that has my socket id and then again once you get the socket
it's already connected it already has the data on it for you to read and you're good to go.
That was about the socket broker and how you can run sockets in the background...windows
...so we hope that this will enable many cools scenarios especially
for peer-to-peer chat...incoming call notification kind of apps?
Next let's look at
a new low overhead path that we have enabled for both tty sockets.
So, when we look at the right...operation on a socket which is when you're
sending data out each riot incurs a transition to kernel
mode core and back into user mode and this?
Sort of creates a lot of overhead in that right path and that's
...apps such as vp n apps for
void maps that have many such data buffers being passed out in
...a lot of overhead because of this now in windows stand we have enable a
new pattern that optimizes this frequency of...transitions.
Let's see how we do that.
So, if you're...beginner
programmer or if networking is not really the focus of your
app if you just wanted to write a few data packets out on the socket you will presumably
use a pattern like this you will have a list of buffers that are the package that-you
want-to send out you will
...output stream and then for each of your packets...simply do...is
saying and this is simple and easy to debug it does the job and
you can send the data out however as we noted earlier this leads to a
kernel transition and back for each of your light operations and hence who suffered
...performance a higher performance pattern that exist even back in windows
eight-point one is that you can create and...of your tasks.
And, then for each of your packet you basically
track the right operation as a task but don't wait for the previous
one to complete before issuing the next one that
way let's say you have hundred packets you could just issue all the hundred rights and
then wait on all of them at once and this pattern really helps us in
the operating system to manager packet buffers and do the
kernel transitions in an optimal way so this pattern we have made
even more efficient in windows stand will soon see a demo of how fast how
fast that is an windows...but, note that this pattern only exists for csharp
developers because it uses tasks?
Now there's yet another pattern that we have enable
in windows stand which is using the operation of flush a...
So, essentially you're doing a very similar kind of pattern
your creating all your write operations but instead of using a
task you use and I facing operation with progress.
Now again you have this area of buffers you simply.
Issue all the
...and then finally you call flash facing the behaviour of
flash facing api has changed from windows eight or eight point one to windows
stand in windows eight-point one flush is include return to you immediately
and not guarantee that all your rights have completed whereas in windows
stand the behaviors changed to guarantee that all your rights
have completed and then you can look at whether the status was a success or failure so
the these two patterns that task start...all and
...really enable...much faster performance on sockets.
Some important considerations to node though is that once you have issued all the rights
should be careful not to modify the buffers until all the right
operations of completed because you should sort of think of the operating system
as having ownership of that before for that one and as I mentioned the...
facing pattern only works in windows ten onwards and it only works for certain
classes of sockets so...only works for stream socket and for a connected data
...socket of course for either previous versions of windows
...for other types of sockets can continue to use the tasks dot rate all better.
So, now let's quickly jump into a demo and see how much faster.
So, here I have.
An app that basically compares the sending speed with the batch
sense and without descends and you can of course said the remote address and remote
and point so on the data buffer sizes considerable so let's quickly start the
demo and we observe that the...sense gets done much faster in fact it's four
times as fast as without the bat sense we can also see that even if
increase the data before size which means we are now sending larger packets
it still significantly faster than without the bat sends.
So, you clearly see how much faster...new...enables your code to be.
And, italy empowers.
Void and vp...apps to be much faster on windows...
So, that was an overview of the improvement
...making in the sockets api let's now move over a layer
higher to http and see what improvements we have for you so you might
be familiar with the windows dot web dot http api which has been available since windows and
windows phone eight-point one this is essentially an api that we provide to
implement the http client role on the devices it was design very similar to the
dot net api which has been around for a little while longer and this helps us
minimize the learning curve for developers who are adopting this api.
So, the basic pattern is that you create a single client object and then you can use it to
issue multiple requests to multiple servers.
You can also optional e customize
...object called the http base protocol filter so you can think of the
base protocol filter as being underneath the client empowering the http
communication when you create a client we create a filter underneath
by default and give it to you but you can option the also customize the behaviour of that filter
...you can just create your own filter and completely bypass the os
provider filter and finally you can chain multiple filters so that you can
process...as it's going out
or response as it's coming in for more discussion on the...of multiple
filters of I would point...the windows dot web dot http dot
filters name space documentation msdn
...a really good description of how you can do this...and what is useful...
So, the big news now is that the apis
of windows web http gets http to support starting in windows stan.
So, what is http too I'm sure a lot of you are familiar with this storm as it
is the new evolving standard for http and the next version of
...http one-point-one so
essentially what http to does is that it multiplex is
multiples streams or request response...
In a single tcb connection now why is this faster.
Using the see a single tcp connection means that you incur much fewer
round-trip time to set up a connection every time you need one.
Also there are fewer bites being sent on the wire because http to
uses what is called header compression to minimize the number of header
bites it sending for every request.
finally I would like to point out that http to is no longer something in the distant future
and you can think about it later it's really her a lot of the big players
on the web microsoft google facebook twitter akamai are
already starting to design the web services and upgrade them to http...so this
is really something that's here that's now and we generally need to start developing apps to
take advantage of this if you're more interested in http...there's another talk in
build by rob trace which discusses all of http...in windows stan.
So, let's look at how we enable this...api the best
parties on by default so whether you have an existing
app in the store or if you're writing a new you ap
app you get this for free without any code taint.
We have also built-in negotiations so if let's say the client
...http to the server but the server does not understand http
to it's still http one-point-one the client will automatically
fall back to http one-point-one and your app would never be affected.
However, we do understand that there might be times when the http to
...of the server has a bug or you're just trying to bring of both...and service
endpoints and you're still working through your debugging so it's a single
line of code change to explicitly switch back to http one-point-one will
soon see a code fragment of how to do that and finally we're also working
on enabling http to support in the dot net api so that no matter which
api you choose to write your you ap app you would get http to support built-in.
So, let's quickly look at...code sample as I mentioned before
...is the http base protocol filter that essentially
...all of your http communication after you create that filter
there's a property called max version on that filter and again as I
mention the default value in windows stand is http
tool but you can go ahead and set it to whatever value you like.
Now this max version basically says what the client prefers as
the http version so now you create the new client object you send a request
to the server and now when the server sense you back the response.
You can query the version property often response to understand.
...that you can query the version property of the response to understand what protocol the server
is using and it's very important to note here that even if you specify http
...for the client preference.
Depending on the proxies that are between you and the server and the
server support itself you may not really be talking http tool.
So, let's quickly switch to a demo and see how this works so here I have the
app for http dual.
Let's go ahead and run it.
So, we see like for http one-point-one we are in this
...are basically downloading a set of thumbnail images from
as your website first will use
http one-point-one and we'll see how much time it takes.
Still notice how all the images are coming down in cities that coming
...one by one and that's the typical nature of...one-point-one if I switch to a cb
It just comes on what faster.
I'm making sure not took dash any resources so we can look at it again.
If I downloaded again it takes two-point-three seconds.
But, should...one again?
Index much longer.
Looking at the code as I mentioned before.
There's only this one-line of change where you can simply switch between
...versions being
...one-one and that's it you get http dual...app.
You switch back to...
So, that's all we have for the http api we are really looking forward to
Grace scenarios that developers enable with http
...and we would love to your feedback on how we can improve the api even further to
lead to take advantage of http to.
Next him other we will now go over the improvements and background transfer api thanks
said that was really exciting to see so many improvements in socket
...http now ...
I'm sure you are in all developers are going to use those apis embedded interesting
scenarios but we haven't stopped there we had moved ahead and also
added bunch of new features in the windows networking background transfer
...background transfer as, you know,
it is not new api this is from windows
eight windows eight-point one-time frame the basic api pattern is very simple
you create a background downloaded object and you can you know,
schedule a bunch of background downloads
...uploads using that download object just passing on the uri and the file with
...the cool part is that you know,
this api is network resilient like if you if you if
you're wi-fi connection goes on and off that transfers doesn't fail, you know,
the automatically resume and lets you download large content
like music or video or podcast in the
background a lot of apps like one drive and you know,
music and video apps broadcast apps use this api to download the
content the other piece which is very interesting is the api has in
...intelligence in terms of you know, how much data
... data do you...cellular network has, you know,...ortiz are data plan and,
you know,...data sense and battery's sense of where so we have taken a huge step forward
and added of feature called post-processing in the background transfer
api now what is post-processing it's basically a
and the ability of two-run your application code even when the
user is not able to not using your application at the end of
...transfer so say you have huge
movie which you are downloading at the end of the download the
app wants to do something which earlier it has to do only when the user is
going is using the app now they can do it at the right at the end of the transfered
...end of the download how do we do that we are actually building upon the background
task infrastructure and I will delve a little bit more on that in the future slides
...so what are the scenarios which background post-processing enables one of
the interesting thing which it enables is that it...it gives the
app ability to run automatic processing of the downloaded
files like after the download happened you can process
the file automatically you don't have to wait for the user to come back to your application to
process those files a lot of times a lot of apps have server-side
transaction logic at the end of the download like you purchase
...the music download happens and then you want to send
...acknowledgement to the server to complete
the transaction now it can be done right at the end of the download
you can also add a, you know, customized...
failed transfer retrace background transfer does some amount of retry is forty on your
behalf but if you want to have more control and do some more interesting
teens, you know, during after the download has failed you can do that
using this feature so let's look at what is the programming pattern, you know,
in windows eight-point one the pattern is that was very
simpleyou create a background transfer and then you
have to start those transfers while from your app once the
transfers get started from your app the background process takes over and
transfer the data in the background for your app at the
...what it does is it sendscompletionhandler call back to your
app right now in windows ten what we have done is using
three steps three additional steps you can add a support for
a background post-processing the first step is after you create the background transfers you
have you can create and a background task and completion
trigger and then link the background...can the completion trigger to the transfer before
starting the transfers so in that case what will happen is after the transfer is complete
...will take care of launching
of your completion handler task at the end of the transfer
...the background and you also have a option to handle the completion
...the foreground if you're app is running so that's pretty powerful now let's look at each
and every each of these three steps in little bit more detail with code samples and how do
you do that so the first step is to create a background task completion
triggers so for this what we have done is we have we have introduced a new
a class called background transfer completion group
now doze...people who are familiar with background transfer
epa might to remember that there is something called background
transfer group but this is different from that because it gives it gives
a ability to batch a set of transfers after which a task should be
...so what we do is in this case we
creative simple background transfer completion group then we, you know,
the usual background task apis we create
...the background task but the interesting thing is that we have to set the
trigger of the task to the completion groups trigger so you know,
that's how you will create the task create the completion group and said the tasks
trigger to the completion groups figure the next step would be do
...the background tasks to the transfers
now for that that's also very simple piece of code as usual
we where we usually created download
...do you add the transfers now in the background download
the constructor you can pass on the completion group which it belongs then
you add as usual all the download operation to the to
the downloaded and at the end after adding all the transfers
what we do what you have to do is you have to say completion group dot enable what
this means is really a transaction commit kind of thing so you are indicating
the indicating thatusing after all these transfer...done?
Then only you know,and, respond the tasks...the background tasks.
So, now what do...the task code
...to like one that when the task is launched in the background how do, you know,
which downloads have completed for that you need to just check on
the check on the background transfer completion
...triggersthe trigger details contains the list of downloads there
...completed the similarly if it's upload the trigger details will have a list
of uploads which has competed so using that you can you can now have
control of the downloads which you had
earlier started now you can do interesting post-processing work with a downloads you
want to access the file or you want to send a server acknowledgment you can do all those
all those activities no with some important points to note that?
...the background task which is launched...is a regular background task it is
not something special it isit will be part of the
pool of background tasks which are running in the system so the subject to same
...network court are and it will it will be part of the
...so it can be if there are a lot of background task already runningit
there can be a snot...before that task
...run so we need to we need to the take
the note of that and it also doesn't replace your foreground completion handler
your foreground completion handler still can be run if the
app is running so this just gives an additional option for you to process
your transfers right at the end of in the end of the transfer?
So, let's now quickly look at the demo...
Background transfer post-processing so here in this sample app I
have got three projects as you can see this is the background transfer
the up app which is the foreground app this one is my background transfer
this is a web service which is hosted in as your this is my own web service which
I've written what is the service data is does is it it'sit
...failure in the download so say you say you ask the web service to download
five files from the web service it will induce random failure and,
this is the background task to you know, a process that transfer so if you look at
term so let me run the app ok so in my?
In my background transfer I start ten downloads and...completion group.
And, what it does is it randomly fails and...
...sends toast messages on how many of failed but interestingly as you
could see the download the getting failed but there automatically
Retried and getting succeeded so ultimately all the downloads
are succeeded so how do we do that is through this background task?
So, if you see in this background task what we do is we actually get the
failed downloads and then you know,
retry all the downloads in the background.
So, coming back to the presentation.
So, this is all about the background
...but in addition to that we have done a lot ofother
improvements in other networking apis which are very popular like windows dot
...jason now in this api we had improve
the debugging experience of this api on in visual studio earlier in a
...object you there was no...to see the individual
members while debugging in the watch window now we have added support in the visual
studio to get a access to individual members of the
jayson objects we also have added a new api
for easy serialized...in dc realizing of null values now
the that will help developers too, you know,
process null values much faster and easier
the second thing what we have done in network background transfer epa is that
we have added improved support for removable media
...downloads...is descartes downloads what happens is that we have made
the api intelligent enough to...that the download is happening on
a removal media and then move the temporary files to the
destination location so that...download is faster and completes quicker we have done
some more improvements in the sockets api one of the key improvement which
...have done is now at the socket api levelyou-can
id you can indicate a client certificate for authentication
of the socket this was a huge developer ask and we have added it into
...api so in the stream socket you can now
setup client certificate for authentication also we have added support
...sharing in the data...circuit which is also a very powerful,
powerful feature so with that we would
appreciate your feedback and requests for new features on the networking api
...you can send that to comments on this channel
online video or you can blog your ideas in wb dev user
...dot com also you can voice...feedback and...and, your request
...new feature in the windows insider program that we are done for today the good-bye.